<chapter id="starting">
  <title>Getting Started With <literal>Veil2</literal> (STEP 1)</title>
  <para>
    This section aims to help you get <literal>Veil2</literal>
    installed on your database server, and into your database.
  </para>
  <sect1 id="installation">
    <title>Installing <literal>Veil2</literal></title>
    <para>
      Since version 0.9.1, <literal>Veil2</literal> can and
      should be installed as a PostgreSQL extension.  It is available
      from <ulink url="https://pgxn.org/">PGXN</ulink> the PostgreSQL
      Extension Network.
    </para>
    <para>
      Alternatively it can be downloaded from github and built
      locally.  For more on this see the <link
      linkend="for_developers">developers section</link>.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="pgxn_install_with_client">
      <title>Installing To Your Server Using The <literal>pgxn</literal> Client</title>
      <para>
	If you have the <literal>pgxn</literal> client available on
	your database server you can simply do this:
	<programlisting>
# pgxn install veil2
	</programlisting>
	If not, you can download <literal>Veil2</literal> from PGXN or
	github, and then build and install it locally as described
	<link linkend="for_developers">here</link>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="pgxn_install_with_client">
      <title>Per-Database Install</title>
      <para>
	Installing the <literal>Veil2</literal> extension in a given
	database is done with the following command, eg from
	<literal>psql</literal>:
	<programlisting>
dbname# create extension veil2 cascade;
	</programlisting>
	Note that <literal>cascade</literal> is used to ensure that
	<literal>Veil2</literal>'s extension dependencies are also
	installed.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="next_steps">
    <title>Next Steps</title>
    <para>
      The following chapters describe in detail the next steps to take
      in securing your database with <literal>Veil2</literal>.  These
      chapters assume that you will be looking at the
      <literal>Veil2</literal> demos for examples.  You can find the
      demo files on your database server by executing the following
      query:
	<programlisting>
dbname# select * from <link linkend="view_sql_files">veil2.sql_files</link>;
	</programlisting>
      This lists a number of files that you can take a look at.  There
      are 3 files that you should take copies of:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    the <literal>Veil2</literal> demo creation script;
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This is referenced from most of the following chapters,
	    and provides useful, though often incomplete, examples of
	    what needs to be done at each step.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    the <literal>Veil2</literal> minimal-demo creation script;
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This provides a complete example of the simplest possible
	    <literal>Veil2</literal> installation.  It avoids using
	    the more sophisticated features of
	    <literal>Veil2</literal> but by virtue of being a complete
	    implementation may provide more helpful code examples.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    the <literal>Veil2</literal> implementation template.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This is a template script for you to use as the basis of
	    your <literal>Veil2</literal> implementation.  It
	    identifies all of the steps needed and provides
	    commented-out examples and templates for you to use.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      If you cannot access these files on your database server, you
      can most easily access them from github or by downloading from
      pgxn.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
