<chapter id="how-difficult-is-this">
  <title>How Difficult Is This?</title>
  <para>
    You could be forgiven for thinking, given
    <literal>Veil2</literal>'s capability and sophistication, that it
    would be difficult to set-up and use.  But this is not the case.
    It is not trivial and it does require you to develop a deeper
    understanding of your data than you might choose, but the process
    is well documented and each individual step is simple enough.
  </para>
  <para>
    The best way to get a grip on the complexity and amount of effort
    that would be required is to look at the <link
    linkend="veil_demo">demo app</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    In the spirit of expecting resistance, what follows is a list of
    imagined criticisms of <literal>Veil2</literal> with appropriate
    responses.  This is in place of a FAQ since, at the time of
    writing, no-one has asked any questions.
  </para>
  <sect1 id="frequently-imagined-criticisms-fic">
    <title>Frequently Imagined Criticisms (FIC)</title>
    <para>
      It’s easy to criticize relational security systems and
      implementations as they are not widely used and can be difficult
      to grasp. Here are a few criticisms that have been directed at
      <literal>Veil2</literal>-like implementations.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          It’s too difficult for our application developers to
          understand.
        </para>
        <para>
          Actually, it’s easier for them than having to implement
          application security for themselves.  For the most part,
          they don’t need to understand the details.  Also, they may
          be smarter than you think.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The users won’t understand.
        </para>
        <para>
          They don’t need to.  The security implementation is almost
	  entirely hidden.  But they should be able to understand that
	  assigning a role to a user in a given context, gives that
	  user the ability to perform tasks appropriate to that role.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We’ll need a database specialist to do this.
        </para>
        <para>
          Yes, you will.  And they had better be good at what they do.
          But the time that your database specialist spends on setting
          up your security system with <literal>Veil2</literal> should
          be matched by the amount of time saved by your application
          developers who will no longer have to implement security
          mechanisms themselves.
        </para>
        <para>
	  Furthermore, with a good database specialist available you
	  should end up with a better overall database design as well
	  as one that is well secured.
        </para>
        <para>
	  If you’re not prepared to employ a database specialist then
	  relational security is not for you.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          No-one else does it this way.
        </para>
        <para>
          And how is that working out for them?  The track record of
	  <emphasis>everyone else</emphasis> does not look too good
	  when you start looking closely.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          It’s going to be expensive.
        </para>
        <para>
          Not necessarily.  Your application developers should have an
          easier time of things.  You should end up with a
          higher-quality, and easier-to-maintain application.  There
          will be a need to do some careful thinking about access
          controls, and you will need to document your security model,
          but that is a good thing to do anyway.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We will be held hostage by our database/security expert.
        </para>
        <para>
          Only if you let them.  Documenting your security model is
          essential.  Documenting your administration processes is
          essential.  You should be doing this anyway.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you have the documentation, and you have access to good
          developers who are prepared to read, then you should have no
          problems.  You will need quality control but you have that
          anyway.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          How do we know it’s going to work?
        </para>
        <para>
          Perhaps you could run some tests.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Won’t performance be a problem?
        </para>
        <para>
          Not in the author's experience but you may find otherwise.
          You may need to perform some data denormalizations and you
          will want to analyze some of your queries but there should
          be little performance impact.
        </para>
        <para>
	  If you are concerned, and you should be, try modelling your
	  use-case and test it.  Find your biggest tables and
	  implement a minimal test database that you aim to secure
	  using <literal>Veil2</literal>.  If the big tables perform
	  adequately, then the rest should be a breeze.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There is no expertise available.
        </para>
        <para>
	  Any Postgres specialist who can read this documentation
	  should be able to cope and quickly become an expert.  The
	  underlying principles are all documented.  The code is all
	  documented.  There are documented examples.  There are
	  even <link linkend="contact">contact</link> links.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
