<chapter id="performance">
  <title>Performance</title>
  <para>
    Adding <literal>Veil2</literal> to your database introduces 2
    specific overheads to  your database performance.
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	the overhead of session management;
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	the overhead of privilege testing in your relations.
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>
  <sect1 id="load_perf_data">
    <title>Data For Evaluating Performance</title>
    <para>
      In order to get a feel for the overheads associated with
      <literal>Veil2</literal>, we need some realistic volumes of
      data for roles, privileges, and accessors with their associated
      mappings.  The script, <literal>demo_bulk_data.sql</literal>,
      which can be found as described <link
      linkend="next_steps">here</link> provides a good starting point
      for this.
    </para>
    <para>
      After creating a demo database (as <link
      linkend="veil_demo">described here</link>) you can install this
      data using psql, eg:
      <programlisting>
marc:veil2$ psql -d vpd -f /usr/share/postgresql/12/veil2/demo_bulk_data.sql 
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      This will create around 8000 accessors, around 300 roles, and
      around 2000 privileges, which should be enough to exercise
      the privilege testing and session management functionality.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Session Management Overhead</title>
    <para>
      The two biggest overheads in session management are the use of
      <literal>bcrypt()</literal> for authentication (which is
      CPU-intensive by intent), and the loading of session
      privileges.  In the following evaluation,
      <literal>bcrypt()</literal> is avoided. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Session privileges once loaded (from <link
      linkend="view_session_privileges_v"><literal>veil2.session_privileges_v</literal></link>
      are cached (in <link
      linkend="entity_accessor_privileges_cache"><literal>veil2.accessor_privileges_cache</literal></link>).
      This means that subsequent loading of privileges should be
      considerably faster than the initial one for each accessor.
    </para>
    <para>
      A simple performance checking script <literal>perf.sql</literal>
      is provided in the same directory as the bulk data loading
      script.  Assuming the same directory as the example above you
      would run it as follows:
      <programlisting>
marc:veil2$ psql -d vpd -f /usr/share/postgresql/12/veil2/perf.sql 
Creating sessions: elapsed = 16 milliseconds.
Opening sessions: elapsed = 54 milliseconds.
Re-opening sessions: elapsed = 61 milliseconds.
marc:veil2$ 
      </programlisting>
      The script creates 6 sessions, opens each of them, and then
      re-opens them.  The elapsed times shown are cumulative, in this
      case giving the time to open and initialize the sessions as
      being approximately 40 milliseconds (~7 milliseconds each), with
      the session reloads taking about 7 milliseconds (~1.2
      milliseconds each).  
    </para>
    <para>
      This is on an aging desktop PC with the following CPU spec:
      <programlisting>
vendor_id	: GenuineIntel
cpu family	: 6
model		: 58
model name	: Intel(R) Core(TM) i5-3570K CPU @ 3.40GHz
stepping	: 9
microcode	: 0xc
cpu MHz		: 3411.376
cache size	: 6144 KB
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      It may be possible to further improve the performance by
      implementing more of the session management functions in C,
      though initial experiments yielded only minor gains which, given
      the loss in flexibility resulting from a C implementation, were
      not felt to be worthwhile.
    </para>
    <para>
      Until anyone claims otherwise, the author is going to claim that
      this is fast enough.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Privilege Testing Overhead</title>
    <para>
      For testing the overhead of running privilege tests, you should
      load the performance evaluation data as described <link linkend="load_perf_data">above</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The script <literal>perf2.sql</literal> sets up 3 identical
      tables for performance testing, and runs some simple queries.
      The tables are:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    x;
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This table has no security policy.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    y;
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This table has a minimal security policy, calling <link
	    linkend="func_always_true"><literal>veil2.always_true()</literal></link>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    z.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This table has a security policy using <link
	    linkend="func_i_have_global_priv"><literal>veil2.i_have_global_priv()</literal></link>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Here is the transcript of a performance testing run:
      <programlisting>
marc:veil2$ psql -d vpd -f  /usr/share/postgresql/12/veil2/perf2.sql
Setting up tables...
connecting as Alice...
31|7argrXo++w024hrMnrRwUAnZwvb4i/DN8ZFbF0MMjcg=||t|
Time: 24.037 ms
running tests...
...on x (3 times)...
1995
Time: 0.521 ms
1995
Time: 0.292 ms
1995
Time: 0.265 ms
...on y (3 times)...
1995
Time: 0.520 ms
1995
Time: 0.292 ms
1995
Time: 0.283 ms
result_counts (to keep us honest):
0|0
Time: 0.131 ms
...on z (3 times)...
1995
Time: 0.499 ms
1995
Time: 0.341 ms
1995
Time: 0.302 ms
result_counts again:
0|5985
Time: 0.079 ms
marc:veil2$ 
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      What this shows is that queries for table z have little more
      overhead than table y, which has the smallest possible overhead
      for a table with a security policy.  Based on all of this, the
      author is going to claim that this is pretty damn fast.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since these results look too good to be true, we perform a query
      of <literal>veil2.result_counts()</literal> which shows the
      number of false and true results from the privilege testing
      functions.  This should be seen as proof that the privilege
      tests were actually performed.  Obviously, you can repeat this
      yourself.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Other Privilege Test Functions</title>
      <para>
	The tests above only test
	<literal>veil2.i_have_global_priv()</literal>, which is the
	simplest of the privilege testing functions.  While this may
	seem to be a cheat, testing privileges in other scopes is
	just as fast as testing in the global scope.
      </para>
      <para>
	That said, those functions that check for privileges in
	superior scopes, run a query to discover the appropriate
	superior scopes, and so incur more overhead.  Experience
	suggests that this will still be easily dwarfed by any fetches
	from uncached rows.
      </para>
      <para>
	If your application uses a lot of superior scope tests, or
	those queries are used on large numbers of records, you should
	run your own tests to ensure that performance is adequate.  If
	not you may need to perform some denormalizations to record
	the appropriate superior scope in each row.
      </para>
      <para>
	Even with this caveat though, the author is still going to
	claim that it's fast.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>In Conclusion</title>
    <para>
      Oh my, it's fast!
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
