<chapter id="security">
  <title>Security</title>
  <subtitle>(So, How Secure Is This?)</subtitle>
  <para>
    Although a well-implemented <literal>Veil2</literal>-based VPD
    will give you a more secure system than one without
    <literal>Veil2</literal>, there are some fundamental limits to how
    secure your database can ever be.
  </para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Fundamental Security Weaknesses</title>
    <subtitle>(Game-Over Scenarios)</subtitle>
    <para>
      There are many security threats that <literal>Veil2</literal>
      can do nothing for.  <literal>Veil2</literal> can only limit
      access to data for users that are, or appear to be legitimate.
      Here are some things <literal>Veil2</literal> can't protect
      against:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  an attacker with credentials for the owner of the database
	  objects;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  an attacker with credentials for the postgres account;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  an attacker with credentials for root;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  an attacker who can become root through a local privilege
	  escalation attack;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  an attacker with access to the database filesystem;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  an attacker with access to database backups;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  an attacker with access to a replica/failover/reporting
	  database.
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>So, What Is It Good For?</title>
    <para>
      <literal>Veil2</literal> is designed primarily to protect
      sensitive data from legitimate users.  It is not intended to
      keep attackers out of your systems.  It cannot hope to keep your
      data secure against attacks from state actors, or highly skilled
      black-hat hackers.  
    </para>
    <para>
      It protects sensitive data from overly inquisitive users;
      against opportunist attacks from <ulink
      url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Script_kiddie">script
      kiddies</ulink>; and can greatly limit the damage that can arise
      from a compromised application server.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Compromised Application Server, Really?</title>
    <para>
      Yep.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Problem</title>
      <para>
	If your database is being accessed from a web-based system it
	is in hostile territory.  Typically, your web-facing
	application server will be running in a walled-off part of
	your network which is considered <quote>untrusted</quote>.
	This is often referred to as a <ulink
	url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DMZ_%28computing%29"><literal>DMZ</literal></ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
	This partitioning of your network is to keep servers that are
	publicly accessed from the internet, separate from any
	sensitive infrastructure.  This is partly because of the poor
	history of web application security, and partly from a
	justifiable sense of caution.
      </para>
      <para>
	Servers in the <literal>DMZ</literal> are often viewed as
	disposable, and easily rebuilt and replaced.  The problem
	though, is that these servers must be given access, whether
	directly or indirectly, to your data and therefore to your
	databases.  So, your databases have to accept queries from
	these <quote>untrusted</quote> servers.
      </para>
      <para>
	When everything is secure and working as it should, your
	database will process many different queries on behalf of
	many different users having many different levels of access.
	It is likely that most of your database tables, and most of
	their contents need to be accessible to one legitimate user or
	another.  Which means that the database server generally has
	to provide almost unlimited access to its data, to a server
	that by definition is not to be trusted.
      </para>
      <para>
	Aside: many developers consider web-services to be a solution
	to this, but all they do is add an intermediate layer.
	Whether your web application provides access to different
	aspects of customer data indirectly via multiple web services,
	or directly via a link to the database, the result is the
	same: the web application server has access to
	<emphasis>all</emphasis> of your data.  Although each web
	service can be given its own database account which can limit
	the data that <emphasis>it</emphasis> can see, the aggregation
	of all web services has to provide the same degree of data
	access that a more traditional application would have been
	granted directly in the absence of such web services.
      </para>
      <para>
	What this means is that any breach of your web application
	server will result in an attacker having the same rights to
	your database that your application server has been given, and
	the chances are that your application server needs access to
	almost every relation in your database.
      </para>
      <para>
	In summary: currently acceptable practice is to put
	web-application servers in a special untrusted segment of the
	network, because we don't trust them, and require that database
	servers treat all traffic from them as trusted.  What could
	possibly go wrong?
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The (<literal>Veil2</literal>) Solution</title>
      <para>
	<literal>Veil2</literal> removes the need to trust your
	application server.  As each user must individually
	authenticate to the database server itself, a compromised
	application server is less of a threat.  It does not much
	matter if an attacker can send <literal>select * from
	customers</literal> to the database server if that database
	server is only going to let the attacker see the records for
	which they have appropriate credentials.
      </para>
      <para>
	With <literal>Veil2</literal> an attacker can only access the
	set of data for which they can steal credentials.  If they can
	steal Bob's login credentials, then they can see all of the
	data that Bob can see.  But no more than that.  And they could
	probably <ulink
	url="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/security.png">steal Bob's
	credentials</ulink> without going to the trouble of breaking
	in to the application server.  Furthermore, if you implement
	the <link linkend="report_breaches">reporting of blocked
	accesses</link> as suggested in the <link linkend="tips">tips
	chapter</link>, you will probably be alerted as soon as any
	intruder attempts to access the database.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
