<chapter id="superior_scopes">
  <title>Define Your Scope Hierarchy (STEP 6)</title>
  <para>
    In your database, you are likely to have a hierarchy of <link
    linkend="scopes">scopes</link>.  What this means is that one scope
    is contained within another.  For instance a project scope might be
    contained within the department scope of the department that owns
    the project.  This hierarchy is used in 2 ways:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	for <link linkend="scope-promotion">scope
	promotions</link>;
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	for determining access rights to data within inferior scopes.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    Determining which scopes may be promoted to which other scopes is
    done through the <literal><link
    linkend="view_superior_scopes">superior_scopes</link></literal>
    view.  This identifies, for each scope, what directly superior
    scopes exist.  It does not identify global scope, and does not
    require a recursive query to identify grandparent scopes etc.
    These are handled elsewhere.
  </para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Customizing The <literal>superior_scopes</literal>View</title>
    <para>
      You will need to create a custom version of the <literal><link
      linkend="view_superior_scopes">superior_scopes</link></literal>
      view.  This is done (as described <link
      linkend="custom-views">here</link>) by creating an over-riding
      custom view named <literal>my_superior_scopes</literal>.
      The provided <literal>Veil2</literal> base version of this
      view is simply a placeholder.
    </para>
    <para>
      You will define this view as the union of a number of selects.
      Each select will represent a single type of superior scope.  The
      following example is from the demo.  See STEP 6 in the file
      <literal>demo/veil2_demo--&version;.sql</literal>.
      <programlisting>
create or replace
view veil2.my_superior_scopes (
  scope_type_id, scope_id,
  superior_scope_type_id, superior_scope_id
) as
select 4, party_id,  -- Promote org to corp scope
       3, corp_id
  from demo.parties_tbl -- No join needed to scopes as party_id == scope_id
 where party_type_id = 2
union all
select 4, party_id,  -- Promotion of org to higher org
       4, org_id
  from demo.parties_tbl
 where party_type_id = 2
   and party_id != org_id  -- Cannot promote to self
union all
select 5, s.scope_id,   -- Project to corp promotions
       3, p.corp_id
  from demo.projects p
 inner join veil2.scope_links s
    on s.project_id = p.project_id
union all
select 5, s.scope_id,   -- Project to org promotions
       4, p.org_id
  from demo.projects p
 inner join veil2.scope_links s
    on s.project_id = p.project_id;
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that if you have something like an organizational hierarchy
      in which you want someone that is assigned a role in an
      organizational context, to automatically have those rights in
      all subordinate organizational contexts, you will need to define
      scope promotions within that hierarchy.  This is done by the
      second query in the above union.
    </para>
    <para>
      Any time you redefine this view you should call 
      <literal><link
      linkend="func_init">veil2.init()</link></literal> to
      update the base definition and refresh the materialized views
      that depend on it.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Handle Refresh of Materialized Views</title>
    <para>
      If your scope hierarchy changes in a way that could affect the
      privileges that might be assigned to accessors, you should
      refresh all <link linkend="cache">materialized views and
      caches</link>.  Since determining what sort of updates might
      require this is somewhat complicated, we recommend that
      <emphasis>any</emphasis> change that would result in the <link
      linkend="view_superior_scopes"><literal>veil2.superior_scopes</literal></link>
      view returning different data should result in a full refresh of
      all materialized views.  For this you should call the trigger
      function <link
      linkend="func_refresh_scopes_matviews"><literal>veil2.refresh_scopes_matviews()</literal></link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is assumed that such changes will be rare but if this is not
      the case, and you encounter a performance penalty from having
      the <link
      linkend="view_accessor_privileges_cache"><literal>veil2.accessor_privileges_cache</literal></link>
      cache table releatedly cleared, you may be able to instead of
      truncating that table, selectively delete records based on the
      session contexts that are affected by your changes.  Our
      recommendation is not to tackle this until you know that you
      have a problem.  By then you should have enough local
      <literal>Veil2</literal> expertise that you can easily figure
      our what to do.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
