<chapter id="what-is-relational-security">
  <title>What Is A Relational Security System?</title>
  <para>
    A Relational Security System is one in which access to each piece
    of data and functionality is limited according to the user's
    relationships to that data or functionality.  Access is managed by
    privileges that users aquire by various means and in various
    contexts, and which provide each aquired privilege with a scope,
    which limits the extent to which that privilege applies.
  </para>
  <para>
    Users aquire their privileges in various ways.  There may be a
    basic set of privileges that all users get; some users may be
    members of teams or departments and their roles in those things
    may give them implied privilege assignments; and users may be
    granted specific roles explictly.  Even with explicit role
    assignments, those assignments may occur in different contexts
    giving the user access to greater or smaller subsets of data: you
    might be a manager for a project, within a department or division,
    or company-wide.  The same privileges would apply in each case,
    but their scope would apply to larger or smaller sets of data.
  </para>
  <para>
    For example, you may be given the <literal>select user
    data</literal> privilege in a scope that grants you access to
    only your user data (<emphasis>personal scope</emphasis>); or to
    only user data for users employed in your department
    (<emphasis>departmental scope</emphasis>).  You may even have the
    same privilege assigned in multiple distinct scopes.
  </para>
  <para>
    Scopes may be created from almost any definable subset of your
    data.  Mostly they are based on the relationships of your users
    with their data, though they need not be.  Typically, scopes are
    defined in terms of parties and their relationships either to
    other parties, or to specific artifacts described by your
    database.  For example, a person's relationship to the company
    they work for, or their membership of a department or project team.
  </para>
  <para>
    Having scopes associated with privileges means that the
    granularity of access controls can be as coarse or as fine as the
    data demands, and it means that there is rarely the need for more
    complex access checks than "do I have privilege X in scope Y?".
  </para>
  <para>
    Instead of having privileges which imply conditional rule checks,
    such as the privilege to
    <emphasis>maintain-a-project-if-the-user-is-a-member-of-the-project-team</emphasis>,
    privileges can effectively contain their conditionality through
    their scope. 
  </para>
</chapter>
