<sect1 id="whatis">
  <title>What is <literal>Veil2</literal> And What Does It Provide?</title>
  <para>
    <literal>Veil2</literal> is a collection of database objects that
    provides an implementation of roles, privileges, contexts, scopes
    and session management that can be used with minimal extra
    implementation work.
  </para>
  <para>
    It links to your database through functions, triggers and foreign
    keys, and provides fast mechanisms to identify, load and test a
    user's privileges.  Much of this is easily extensible through
    built-in mechanisms but even where it is not, you should feel free
    to modify the code yourself to match your needs.
  </para>
  <para id="hack-it-yourself">
    It is important to realize at this point that
    <literal>Veil2</literal> is not an application or a product.  It
    is a framework for <emphasis>you</emphasis> to build on.  If there
    are updates or bug-fixes they will be to specific pieces of
    functionality which you can choose to replace piecemeal or not at
    all (this document will be updated to describe each such update
    in detail).  There is no rolling-release or automated update
    for you to worry about breaking, and all of its parts are
    user-serviceable.  You will not void your warranty by tweaking it
    as there is no warranty.  Once you have taken it out of the box it
    is yours and you can and should (subject to the terms of the GPL
    V3) treat it as such.  You are expected to add columns to the
    tables, and add new tables and new functionality.  You are
    expected to add to the session management functions to meet your
    own requirements (but if you want to distribute your changes,
    they must be under the same license).  So have at it!
  </para>
  <para>
    There is various documentation to help you with this:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>this document, especially the setup sections starting
      <link linkend="setup">here</link>;</listitem>
      <listitem>comments in the database objects;</listitem>
      <listitem>comments in the <literal>Veil2</literal> creation
      scripts;</listitem> 
      <listitem>the (commented) <literal>Veil2</literal> demo.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    You should familiarize yourself with at least this document and
    the <link linkend="veil_demo">demo</link> before starting out on
    your implementation.
  </para>
  <sect2>
    <title>How Does It Work?</title>
    <para>
      <literal>Veil2</literal> works by:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  ensuring the database knows which user is connected;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  providing a set of contextual privileges to each user;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  providing a fast means of testing a user's privileges;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  individually securing each accessible relation using
	  privilege tests.
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      What this means is that when Alice tries to select the user
      record for Bob, Alice will only see that record if she has been
      assigned the necessary privilege to view Bob's user record in an
      appropriate context.  As each user's privilege assignments will
      be different, each user will see a different subset of data.
    </para>
    <sect3>
      <title>Knowing The User</title>
      <para>
	<literal>Veil2</literal> provides session management functions
	for both <link
	linkend="dedicated_session_management">dedicated</link> and
	<link linkend="shared_session_management">shared</link>
	database connections.  It is up to the user or the user's
	application to ensure that the session protocols are followed.
	If they are not, the user will have access to no data.
      </para>
      <para>
	By calling the appropriate session management functions, with
	appropriate authentication tokens, <literal>Veil2</literal>
	session parameters will be set up in temporary tables.  These
	session parameters include session privileges with one record
	for each scope in which the user has such privileges.
      </para>
      <para>
	The set of privileges in each scope is stored in a single
	bitmap.  This is a space-efficient array of numbered bits,
	with each bit indicating the presence or absence of a
	privilege.  Tests for the presence of a privilege in a bitmap
	are very fast.
      </para>
      <para>
	At the start of each session, the user's privileges are
	determined.  This is based upon the roles that have been
	assigned to them, and the contexts of those role assignments.
	To make this process as fast as possible a number of
	materialized views are used which map roles to their sets of
	privileges in various contexts.  By loading from these
	materialized views, the overhead of determining a large set of
	potential privileges is much reduced, and since the
	materialized views record sets of privileges in bitmaps,
	rather than individual records, this overhead becomes quite
	manageable.  The materialized views are automatically updated
	whenever role->role and role->privilege assignments are
	modified which will tend to be relatively infrequently.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Contextual Privileges Per User</title>
      <para>
	Each privilege assigned to a user operates within a scope that
	depends on the context in which it was assigned.  Some
	scopes will allow all records in a table to be seen or
	manipulated and some will allow large, small or smaller
	subsets of data to be seen.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Fast Privilege Testing</title>
      <para>
	As stated above, the set of privileges in each scope is stored
	in a bitmap, and tests for the presence of a privilege in the
	bitmap are very fast.  The security rules for a relation will
	typically be defined something like this (from the demo):
	<programlisting>
alter table demo.projects enable row level security;

create policy projects__select
    on demo.projects
   for select
 using (   veil2.i_have_global_priv(21)
        or veil2.i_have_priv_in_scope(21, 3, corp_id)
        or veil2.i_have_priv_in_scope(21, 4, org_id)
        or veil2.i_have_priv_in_scope(21, 5, project_id));
	</programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
	Each of the test functions is checking whether the user has
	the privilege, <literal>select projects</literal>, to view the
	current record.  Tests are made in global scope, then corp
	scope of the owning corp, then org scope of the owning org,
	and finally in project scope of the project itself.  Each of 
	these tests causes a different bitmap in the users session
	privileges to be checked.
      </para>
      <para>
	Although having so many tests performed for each record
	returned might seem like a significant overhead, in fact it is
	small compared with the cost of retrieving the record in the
	first place and will often be effectively unmeasurable.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Individually Securing Each Relation</title>
      <para>
	Every table and view is given its own individual security
	definition.  For tables, they will be much as shown above but
	will include definitions for insert, update and delete as well
	as select, as shown above.
      </para>
      <para>
	Views are secured in a similar way, but with the privilege
	testing functions defined in the view itself.  Sometimes using
	views can improve the performance of the privilege tests as
	they can be incorporated more deeply within the view, meaning
	that the tests do not have to be executed for every row
	returned.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Refactoring Your Systems To Use <literal>Veil2</literal></title>
    <para>
      Integrating your systems with <literal>Veil2</literal> is not a
      trivial task.
    </para>
    <para>
      This section describes the major areas that you will need to
      address in order to protect an existing system with
      <literal>Veil2</literal>.  This is intended as an introduction
      to the process solely in order to give you a feel for what is
      required.  The process is covered in much more detail <link
      linkend="setup">later</link>.
    </para>
    <sect3>
      <title>Web Session Management</title>
      <para>
	The <literal>Veil2</literal>-protected database needs to know
	which user is accessing it all times.  It provides a
	session-management protocol for use from web applications.
	Your web application will have to provide handling of this
	session management protocol.  Generally this will be handled
	as triggers or hooks into the database connection pool
	management.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Integration of Role Handling</title>
      <para>
	<literal>Veil2</literal> has its own view of what roles should
	do and look like.  If your own system uses roles for its
	existing access control purposes, you will have to somehow
	integrate your system's role requirements with those of
	<literal>Veil2</literal>.  You essentially have three choices:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Bring your roles to <literal>Veil2</literal>. 
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Make your roles the source of <literal>Veil2</literal>
	      roles.  Use triggers and Foreign Key (FK) constraints to
	      make and maintain copies of your roles within
	      <literal>Veil2</literal>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Make <literal>Veil2</literal> the source of your
	      system's roles.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Update <literal>Veil2</literal>'s roles to handle whatever
	      extra data your system needs, and replace your existing
	      role objects with views onto the
	      <literal>Veil2</literal> roles.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Refactor your system to only use
	      <literal>Veil2</literal> roles. 
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      As with the previous option you will probably need to
	      extend the <literal>Veil2</literal> tables to add extra
	      fields for the needs of your existing system.  The
	      advantage of this is that you will end up with a cleaner
	      system, with fewer moving parts.  The downside is that
	      your applications will probably require more refactoring.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	This, depending on how it is tackled, has the potential to be
	the most difficult and invasive of all the changes you will
	need to make.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Integration of Security Contexts</title>
      <para>
	For every type of security context that you wish to provide,
	you will need to provide a link from your existing tables back
	to <literal>Veil2</literal>.  This will be handled with
	triggers and FK-constraints.  There are examples of how this
	may be done in the demo.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Integration of Users</title>
      <para>
	All of your users must be associated with
	<literal>Veil2</literal> accessors (users who access your
	database), and any existing credentials must be migrated.
	Again this can be handled by triggers and FK-constraints, and
	the demo provides examples.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Performance Denormalizations</title>
      <para>
	You will be applying access control to each relation in your
	system.  Some of them may benefit from data denormalization to
	improve the performance of the security tests.  Typically you
	may want to add ownership columns to some tables so that
	ownership can be determined without the need for extra joins.
	If an access control function has to perform extra queries for
	each row returned, performance may suffer.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Authentication</title>
      <para>
	You may need to implement a new authentication system for
	users.  Or the built-in <ulink
	url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bcrypt">bcrypt</ulink>
	implementation may be enough. 
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Development/Tightening of Access Controls</title>
      <para>
	Once you have everything integrated, you will be able to use
	your system.  Create a super-role that allows all access and
	assign it to all of your users in the global context: your
	system will work exactly as it did before.  Now you can begin
	tightening your access controls.
      </para>
      <para>
	Create appropriate roles one function at a time and ensure
	that they have sufficient access to get the job done.  Assign
	these in the lowest security contexts possible and ensure that
	they work.  Check that they work in higher contexts.  Remove
	any existing code that implements access controls for that
	functionality.  If all is well, remove those privileges from
	your super-role and ensure that everyone can still do their
	jobs.  Rinse and repeat.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
